"Soul Food That’s
Good for the Soul"
The burden of cardiovascular disease
in the African American community
remains high and is a primary
cause of disparities
in life expectancy between
African Americans and whites.
Why is there such
an excess burden?
Because of an excess burden
of risk factors, for example,
high blood pressure, diabetes,
obesity, and high cholesterol.
And what’s underlying
those risk factors?
Much can be traced
back to diet.
Among the ethnic groups,
the proportions of people
meeting healthy diet
recommendations
were generally lowest
among Blacks.
In this national survey,
most Black Americans
were found to be eating
a particularly poor diet,
as defined by
the American Heart Association.
African Americans
may face unique challenges
to adherence to dietary
recommendations,
and one such challenge
is an alignment
with a cultural tradition
of “soul food.”
Now some soul food components
are fantastic.
You can’t get much healthier than
collard greens and sweet potatoes,
tomatoes, legumes (dried peas
and beans like black-eyed peas),
watermelon, blackberries,
corn, and okra.
It’s all making me hungry.
But conversely, soul food
can also be high
in added fats, sugars,
and salt, with prominent use
of high-fat meats not to mention
the use of deep frying.
So, like fried
chicken and chitlins,
which are pig intestines,
foods that can be high
in sodium and saturated fat—
dietary factors linked
to chronic disease.
Where did the pig intestines
custom come from?
You have to trace the roots.
Soul food is what the enslaved
Africans were forced
to come up with in the Deep South
to survive during slavery.
That’s in stark contrast
to traditional West African diets
where they come from, which
were predominantly plant-based,
centered on a foundation
of greens and fruits and legumes
and nuts and vegetables, and whole
grains, and even more vegetables.
However, these traditions
have been westernized,
bastardized into a diet
high in fried foods,
sweetened beverages,
and red and processed meats.
But the good news is more
and more African Americans
are adopting plant-based diets
to combat their health problems,
helped by a growing movement
of vegan soul food restaurants
that serve healthier,
plant-based meals.
Soul food scholar Adrian Miller
even wrote that after eating
his way across the country,
it was clear to him
that soul food’s creative energy
burns brightest in restaurants
that are targeting upscale,
vegetarian, or vegan clientele.
Are they reaching the people
who need it most, though?
Well, they do
tend to be located
in higher African American,
higher poverty areas.
A signiﬁcant number
of restaurants were classiﬁed
in food desert zones, where
there’s a dearth of supermarkets,
implying their potential
to provide healthier meals
to residents in the
surrounding neighborhoods.
Therefore, having more
vegan soul food restaurants
and growing movements
centered on Black veganism,
may provide opportunities
to inﬂuence the nutrition habits
in the African American community,
especially since some
are even able to offer
cooking classes.
So, establishing public
health partnerships
with vegan soul food
restaurants to get more
African American adults
to eat plant-based foods
could be a promising
first step in reducing
some of the Black/white
health disparities.
“We’re not meat
shamers,” said owners
of vegan soul
food restaurants
promoting healthy eating in the
African American community.
“We’re plant pushers,” trying
to tie the best of soul food’s origins
to a fourteenth century
plant-centric West African diet,
in hopes of making people feel
that being vegan is in fact
a legitimate part of Black
culture and Black identity.
Even potentially tying
into the concept of social justice,
in an attempt to reverse the eﬀects
of targeted marketing eﬀorts
by fast food companies to children
in communities of color.
This movement has been helped
by a plant-positive
who's who of Black culture,
not just luminaries like
like Coretta Scott King
and Cory Booker,
but the likes of NBA stars,
Samuel L. Jackson, and Beyoncé,
and influentially the late
activist Dick Gregory,
known in popular
culture as a comedian,
but was also an outspoken
vegan health advocate
influenced by Alvenia Fulton
who imagined soul food
that was actually
good for the soul.
Instead of celebrating
the fact that slaveholders
denied enslaved people
access to quality foods,
she persuaded
Black communities
to view food as an agent
of health and healing,
advocating fresh,
whole foods as the path
to alleviating or reversing
the crippling burden
of chronic disease.
Black vegetarians and vegans
are showing a plant-based diet
isn’t just for white people—
and never was.
In fact, you can go back centuries
to The Liberator back in the 1800s,
the abolitionist publication
where William Lloyd Garrison
wrote in his famous essay:
"I will be as harsh as truth,
and as uncompromising as justice."
Well, in an 1853 issue,
it was written that:
“A man whose stomach is crammed
with animal abominations…
can no more appreciate lofty moral
and intellectual teachings,
than a swine can appreciate
pearl necklaces.
Logic, humor, and eloquence
are wasted on such persons.”
"If only the American people
took more thought
what they should eat
and drink, obeying the rules
impressed upon them
by experience and science,"
(by which they meant
a vegetarian diet),
(America) "would be half-converted
to Anti-Slavery, Peace,
Temperance, Land Reform,
Woman’s Rights, etc., in a single year."